Robert E. Lee Papers WLU.Coll.0064
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
- Letters from Robert E. Lee, 1833-1870 (Box 1-4B)
  - Letters from Robert E. Lee, 1869-1870 (Box 4)
    - Robert E. Lee to W. L. Marshall, 1870-04-08 (Box 4, Folder 283)
    - Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee, 1870-04-18 (Box 4, Folder 284)
    - Robert E. Lee to William Preston Johnston, 1870-04-21 (Box 4, Folder 285)
    - Robert E. Lee to Angus Neal Gordon, 1870-06-04 (Box 4, Folder 286)
    - Robert E. Lee to Cassius Francis Lee, 1870-06-06 (Box 4, Folder 287)
    - Robert E. Lee to Unnamed Parent, 1870-06-27 (Box 4, Folder 288)
    - Robert E. Lee to T. A. Bartlette, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 289)
    - Robert E. Lee to John Laws, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 290)
    - Robert E. Lee to John L. Campbell, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 291)
    - Robert E. Lee to Fanny Butler, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 292)
    - Copy of newspaper column featuring Letter to W. H. Barrow, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 293)
    - Robert E. Lee to H. A. Tayloe, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 294)
    - Robert E. Lee to Washington Chaney, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 295)
    - Robert E. Lee to Joseph G. Steele, 1870-06-28 (Box 4, Folder 296)
    - Robert E. Lee to Miss A. H. Nichols, 1870-08-06 (Box 4, Folder 297)
    - Robert E. Lee to George T. Denison, 1870-08-06 (Box 4, Folder 298)
    - Robert E. Lee to John Lyle Campbell, 1870-08-23 (Box 4, Folder 299)
    - Robert E. Lee to Maggie Smith, 1870-09-09 (Box 4, Folder 300)
    - Robert E. Lee to Albert Pike, 1870-09-09 (Box 4, Folder 301)
    - Robert E. Lee to William Nelson Pendleton, 1870-09-12 (Box 4, Folder 302)
    - Robert E. Lee to Fitzhugh Lee, 1870-09-19 (Box 4, Folder 303)
    - Robert E. Lee to Ann L. Jones, 1870-09-23 (Box 4, Folder 304)
    - Robert E. Lee to Samuel H. Tagart, 1870-09-28 (Box 4, Folder 305)
    - Lennig Collection I and II, 1842 - 1867 (Box 4, Folder 307)
    - Lennig Collection II, 1859 - 1870 (Box 4, Folder 308)
    - Robert E. Lee to Sally Spottswood Crute, N. D. (Box 4, Folder 306)
  - Penn Letterbook (LB-1) (Box 4A)
  - Copied Letterbooks (Box 4B)
- Non-correspondence by or from Robert E. Lee (Box 5-6)
  - Non-correspondence by or from Robert E. Lee (Box 5)
    - Furlough Approved, 1829-06-16 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Furlough Approved for Cadet Franklin E. Hunt by Cadet Adjutant R.E. Lee, 1829-06-16; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); United States Military Academy (Box 5, Folder 1)
        This furlough request approval from West Point Military Acedemy is addressed to cadet Franklin E. Hunt. It details the nature of the furlough request, the dates of its extent, and the location of teh request. It is signed by R.E. Lee who was serving as Cadet Adjutant at the time. The second page of the document details the current standing of cadet Hunt's debt with the school as well as his payment from the United States government.
    - Receipt for Services for St. Louis Harbor, 1838-03-31 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Receipt for Services for St. Louis Harbor, 1838-03-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 2)
        The receipt made on behalf of a $2.25 purchase from Philip Hefs for materials for the harbor of St. Louis, MO and the Mississippi River on March 31, 1838. It is certified by R.E. Lee, who was supervising engineer for navigation on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, MO at the time. Lee Served 26 years in the US Army Corps of Engineers starting in 1837.
    - Receipt for Articles for Improvement of Mississippi River, 1838-04-30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Receipt for Articles for Improvement of Mississippi River, 1838-04-30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        The receipt made for a $12.42 taxation on Titus Hale for access the Mississippi River on April 30, 1838. It is certified by R.E. Lee, who was supervising engineer for navigation on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, MO at the time. Lee Served 26 years in the US Army Corps of Engineers starting in 1837.
    - Receipt of Articles for St. Louis Harbor, 1838-05-31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Receipt of Articles for St. Louis Harbor, 1838-05-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 4)
        The receipt made for a $81.63 and $39.38 taxation on B. Brown for access the harbor of St. Louis, MO and the Mississippi River in May of 1838. The charges are for anchored boats and the access of stone drills. It is certified by R.E. Lee, who was supervising engineer for navigation on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, MO at the time. Lee Served 26 years in the US Army Corps of Engineers starting in 1837.
    - Receipt for Articles for Improvement of Mississippi River, 1838-06-12 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Receipt for Articles for Improvement of Mississippi River, 1838-06-12; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 5)
        The receipt made for a $47.50 purchase from J. Swan of the steamboat "St. Louis" for materials for the improvement the Mississippi River on June 12, 1838. The purchase is for 10 bales of oakum stored aboard, as well as a "dragage" fee. It is certified by R.E. Lee, who was supervising engineer for navigation on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, MO at the time. Lee Served 26 years in the US Army Corps of Engineers starting in 1837.
    - Receipt for Articles for St. Louis Harbor, 1838-07-21 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Receipt for Articles for St. Louis Harbor, 1838-07-21; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 6)
        The receipt made for a $3.50 taxation on Leander A. Williams for access the Mississippi River on July 21, 1838. The tax is levied on 500 bricks stored aboard to be used to construct a chimney for a blacksmith shop. It is certified by R.E. Lee, who was supervising engineer for navigation on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, MO at the time. Lee Served 26 years in the US Army Corps of Engineers starting in 1837.
    - Personal Check, 1939-06-11 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Personal Check, 1939-06-11 (Box 5, Folder 7)
        This is a personal check made out to Robert E. Lee for $25 on June 11, 1839. The check is from the Bank of the State of Missouri based in St. Louis, MO.
    - Receipt of Articles for Improvement of the Mississippi River, 1839-08-14 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Receipt of Articles for Improvement of the Mississippi River, 1839-04-14; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 8)
        The receipt made for a $44.66 taxation on E. A. Tracy for access the Mississippi River on August 14, 1839. The tax is levied on 2 sacks of coffee stored aboard. It is certified by R.E. Lee, who was supervising engineer for navigation on the Mississippi River in St. Louis, MO at the time. Lee Served 26 years in the US Army Corps of Engineers starting in 1837.
    - Receipt for Articles for Fort Hudson, NY, 1841-06-30 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Receipt for Articles for Fort Hudson, NY, 1841-06-30; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 9)
        This is a receipt for assorted materials to be used in the construction of Fort Hudson in New York. The material was received by Captain R. E. Lee on behalf of the US Corps of Engineers for the sum of $25.34. The material included pick axes, water pails, and various construction materials. The materials were purchased from James C. Curch.
    - Personal Check, 1841-09-30 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Personal Check, 1841-09-30; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 10)
        This is a personal check made out by Robert E. Lee to Henry Weaver for the sum of $12.37. It comes from the New York Bank of Commerce and is dated September 30, 1841. The subject line reads as for Fort LaFayette.
    - Ledger Page, Fort Lafayette, NY, 1843-07-07 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Ledger Page, Fort Lafayette, NY, 1843-07-07; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 11)
        This contains a ledger page used by Robert E. Lee as agent for Fort Lafayette. He used the ledger to record the acquisition and dispensation of debts and funds for the fort, and by extension the US government. The stated balance due to the government was $604.96 on July 7, 1843. These records were taken while Lee was serving in the US Army Corps of Engineers.
    - Ledger Page, Battery Hudson, NY, 1844-07-11 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Ledger Page, Battery Hudson, NY, 1844-07-11; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 12)
        This contains a ledger page used by Robert E. Lee as agent for Battery Hudson. He used the ledger to record the acquisition and dispensation of debts and funds for the fort, and by extension the US government. The stated balance due to the government was $648.77 on June 30, 1844. These records were taken while Lee was serving in the US Army Corps of Engineers.
    - Will, 1846-08-31 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Included in this folder are two copies of Robert E. Lee's will. One copy is a photograph of the original will. The other copy is a published transcription and facsimile of the will, created by Washington and Lee University in 1928.
      - Will, 1846-08-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 13)
        Various copies of the same will written by Robert E. Lee in 1846. In it he details the distribution of his estate after his death. He leaves the entirity of it to his wife, Mary Custis Lee, and subsequently his children after her death. It also includes a Schedule of Property primarily consisting of stocks and shares own in assorted establishments such as the Bank of Virginia, James River and Kanawka Company, and the National Theatre. These are all assigned corresponding monetary values, totalling in an estate of $38,750.00. It also details land division amongst his childre.
        Lee, Mary Custis; Lee family; Lee, George Washington Custis
    - Permission to See Dentist, US Military Academy, 1853-04-15 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Permission to See Dentist, US Military Academy, 1853-04-15; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 14)
        This is a written persmission for Cadet Samuels at West Point Military Academy to leave the academy to go to the hospital and seek out help from a dentist on April 15, 1853 by Robert E. Lee.
    - Ledger Page, US Military Academy, 1854-05-03 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Ledger Page, US Military Academy, 1854-05-03; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 15)
        This ledger page is from the treasury of the US Militart Academy at West Point. It details various articles acquired by the academy and their corresponding price and quantities. It is initialed by Robert E. Lee for approval, as he was serving as Superintendent of the academy at the time. The lower half of the page includes, in red ink, details highlighting the relevance of the initials. These details were likely added years later.
        The reverse side of the page consists of a table of expenses used for the academy.
        United States Military Academy
    - List of Bonds and Stocks, 1855 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - List of Bonds and Stocks, 1855 (Box 5, Folder 16)
        This document contains a complete list of all bonds, shares, and stocks in the ownership of Robert E. Lee. Each stock or bond lists the date of its purchase and date of maturity where applicable. It also details the monetary value of the stocks.
    - Lee's Commission as Lt. Col. US Army, 1855-03-03 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Lee's Commission as Lt. Col. US Army, 1855-03-03; United States. Army (Box 5, Folder 17)
        This is the official commission by the United States Army extended to Robert E. Lee making him a lieutenant colonel. The document is signed by President Franklin Pierce. This is a photographic copy of the original commission.
    - Quarterly Account, US Military Academy, 1855-03-31 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Quarterly Account, US Military Academy, 1855-03-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 18)
        This is a quarterly report for the United States Military Academy compiled and apporved by superintendent Robert E. Lee on March 31, 1855. The report details the expenses for the academy for its fiscal quarter. The report lists major details of expense and their individual costs. The total expenses listed for the quarter total $29,036.10.
    - General Orders No. 2 Assigning Lee Command of the Dept of Texas, 1860-02-06 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - General Orders No. 2 Assigning Lee Command of the Dept of Texas, 1860-02-06 (Box 5, Folder 19)
        This document is a general orders issued by the United States Army Headquarters in New York, NY on February 6, 1860. The orders state that Brevet Colonel Robert E. Lee of the 2nd Cavalry has been given command of teh Department of Texas in order to repar the headquarters of the department and assume command. The orders were given by Lieutenant General H. L. Scott, acting Assistant Adjutant Genearal.
    - General Orders No. 59, 1863-05-07 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - General Orders no. 59, 1863-05-07; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 20)
        This document is a set of general orders issued by General Robert E. Lee to the Confederate Army of Northern Virginia on May 7, 1863. The orders consist of praises for the army's recent victories in battle, as well as time off for the coming Sunday for worship. It goes on to relay a letter from Confederate President Jefferson Davis to the army congratulating them on their victories.
        Confederate States of America. Army
    - General Orders, No. 103, 1863-12-07 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - General Orders, No. 103, 1863-12-07; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 21)
        This document is a set of general orders addressing the Confederat Army of Northern Virginia penned by Robert E. Lee on December 7, 1863. The contents primarily highlight the bravery of the Confederate Army members as well as their perceived religious duty. Lee describes what he believes to believes to be a holy duty of the Confederate officers and expresses deep belief in the presence of God with them.
    - General Orders No. 4, 1865-02-22 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - General Orders No. 4, 1865-02-22; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 22)
        This document is a set of general orders issued by Robert E. Lee to the Confederate Army on February 22, 1865. These orders are a set of new standards to observe in the face of waning supplies and troops. The orders set out that vacant positions are to be filled as soon as possible upon their opening with troops from the rear. Lee goes on to explain new punishment and more stringent rules over any disobedience or evasion of duty.
    - General Orders No. 9 Facsimiles, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - General Orders No. 9 Facsimiles, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 23)
        This document is a copy of General Orders No. 9 issued by Robert E. Lee to the Army of Northern Virginia on April 10, 1865 following the Confederate surrender to General Grant. In it he details the pride and approval of the vigor with which his troops fought, as well as briefly relaying the surrender to Union forces in delicate language to avoid a defeated tone. He ends it by bidding farewell to his troops as the Army of Northern Virginia is dissolved.
        This copy is a published facsimile.
    - General Orders No. 9 Bouldin Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - General Orders No. 9 Bouldin Copy, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 24)
        The copy is a soldier's copy, accompanied by scanned facsimiles.
    - General Orders No. 9 Bouldin Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - General Orders No. 9 Bouldin Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - General Orders No. 9 Fields' Summary, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - General Orders No. 9 Fields' Summary, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - General Orders No. 9 Huntter Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - General Orders No. 9 Huntter Copy, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - General Orders No. 9 Owen Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - General Orders No. 9 Owen Copy, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - General Orders No. 9 Washington and Lee Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - General Orders No. 9 Washington and Lee Copy, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - General Orders No. 9 Washington and Lee Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - General Orders No. 9 Washington and Lee Copy, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - General Orders No. 9, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - General Orders No. 9, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - General Orders No. 9 Unidentified Copies, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      - General Orders No. 9 Unidentified Copies, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - General Orders No. 9 Unidentified Copy, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 32a)
      - General Orders No. 9 Unidentified Copy, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 32a)
    - General Orders No. 9, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - General Orders No. 9, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Confederate Notes Carried by Robert E. Lee at Appomattox, 1865-04-10 (Box 5, Folder 33a)
      - Confederate Notes Carried by Robert E. Lee at Appomattox, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Confederate States of America (Box 5, Folder 33a)
        These are two $20 bank notes from the Confederate States of America. These were carried by Robert E. Lee when signing the surrender at Appomattox to General Grant on April 10, 1865.
    - Receipts for Salary, 1865-1870 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1865-10-14; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1865-11-15; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $169. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-01-25; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $286. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-02-13; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $360. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-07-09; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $253.20. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-07-11; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $750. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-09-22; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Facsimile of Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-09-22; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt facsimile is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $750. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $1500. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $100. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1866-10-04; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $300. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1867-02-09; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $150. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1867-07-08; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $463.86. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1867-04-08; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1868-02-20; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Facsimile Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1868-02-20; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This facsimile of a receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $750. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1868-06-01; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1868-06-01; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $250. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James K. Edmondson.
      - Salary Receipt from James K. Edmondson, 1868; Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - Salary Receipt from James M. Leech, 1869-07-02; Leech, J. M. (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $408.95. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James M. Leech.
      - Salary Receipt from James M. Leech, 1870-07-27; Leech, J. M. (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $1500. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James M. Leech.
      - Facsimile Salary Receipt from James M. Leech, 1870-07-27; Leech, J. M. (Box 5, Folder 34)
        This receipt facsimile is for the salary of Robert E. Lee for his services at Washington College for $1500. It was created by Washington College Treasurer, James M. Leech.
    - Memorandum Book: Directory of Addresses, 1866 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Memorandum Book: Directory of Addresses, 1866; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 36)
        This memorandum book contains several notes written by Robert E. Lee during his tenure at Washington College, as well as a set of names and addresses of those he had corresponded with. The memos range from financial management of college resources to Lee's personal thoughts on the role of education in the fabric of society. The list of names and corresponding addresses appears to be composed of various people Lee remained in contact with, some of which being professors and others being former Confederate officers.
        The written memos are written beginning on one side of the memo book while the names and addresses begin on the reverse side.